# Dr Declan A Valters

Research Software Engineer - Global Change Research Institute - University of Edinburgh dvalts.io • declan.valters@ed.ac.uk • github.com/dvalters

### **Research Software Interests**

I am a scientific software engineer interested in atmospheric, hydrological, and geomorphological modelling, as well as topographic data analysis. I am interested particularly in the links between weather and land surface processes and the development of numerical models that underpin research in land surface dynamics using highperformance computing.

### **Employment**

• Research Software Engineer School of Geosciences

• Scientific Software Engineer Modelling Infrastructure Support Systems

• Software Developer (PhD work placement) Satellite Applications

University of Edinburgh

November 2017 – present

**Met Office** March 2017 - October 2017

Met Office

*June* 2015 – October 2015

### Education

PhD in Earth, Atmospheric, and Environmental Science

Thesis: Modelling catchment sensitivity to rainfall resolution and erosional parameterisation in simulations of flash floods in the UK Supervisors: Prof David Schultz, Dr Simon Brocklehurst

**University of Manchester** 

September 2013 - March 2017

Master in Earth Science (Hons., 1<sup>st</sup> Class)

University of Edinburgh Thesis: Extracting tectonic information using statistical methods of river profile analysis Supervisor: Prof Simon Mudd

2009 - 2013

### **Software Projects**

 Cylc and Rose Scientific workflow management and configuration software

cylc.github.io/cylc March 2017 - November 2017

- Development of the Cylc software package, a scientific workflow manager and scheduler.
- Development of the Rose software framework for configuration of meteorological applications.
- HAIL-CAESAR: A numerical landscape evolution model for HPC PhD software project

dvalts.io/HAIL-CAESAR September 2013 – 2017

- A C++ cellular automaton model ported to HPC (High performance computing) facilities through a shared-memory parallelism model (OpenMP).
- I translated and developed the CAESAR-Lisflood numerical model from a C#/.NET application into a platform-independent code suitable for high-performance computer use such as ensemble simulations and sensitivity analyses.
- Land Surface Dynamics Topographic Toolbox

lsdtopotools.github.io

2012 - Present

*Open source developer/contributor* 

- Object-oriented C++ topographic analysis and modelling package developed with the Land Surface Dynamics research group at Edinburgh. The continuing aim of the project is to implement state-of-the art algorithms as they are published in academic literature. A key aim of LSDTopoTools is to facilitate reproducible scientific data analysis for large topographic datasets.
- My specific role was to develop the statistical analysis tools (C++), visualisation (Python), and automation scripts (Python) for task-farming sensitivity analyses.

Full-stack web developer

July - October, 2015

- Redevelopment of the Met Office/European Meteorological Satellite facility website. A public website used for the retrieval of post-processed satellite data and imagery.
- Designed and implemented a MySQL database for satellite image metadata, integrated with a Javascript front-end for retrieval and rendering of data and imagery.
- I wrote several tools for keeping the database maintained automatically (Shell scripts/Python/PHP) as new data were added.

### **Publications**

### • In preparation

- **Valters**, **D.A.**, et al. (in prep.) *HAIL-CAESAR*: A cellular automaton hydrodynamic landscape evolution model parallelised for shared-memory computing architectures. Geoscientific Model Development
- **Valters**, **D.A.**, et al. (in prep.) *Sensitivity of a flood-inundation model to rainfall distribution and erosional parameterisation.* Hydrology and Earth System Sciences.

#### • 2017

Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Milodowski, D.T., Valters, D.A., Slater, L.J., Hurst, M.D., and Limaye, A.B (2017) Geomorphometric delineation of floodplains and terraces from objectively defined topographic thresholds, Earth Surf. Dynam.

#### 2016

Valters, D.A. (2016). Modelling Geomorphic Systems: Landscape Evolution. In: Cook, S.J., Clarke, L.E. & Nield, J.M. (Eds.) Geomorphological Techniques (Online Edition). British Society for Geomorphology; London, UK. ISSN: 2047-0371.

#### • 2014

Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., Grieve, S.W.D. and Valters, D.A. (2014). A statistical framework
to quantify spatial variation in channel gradients using the integral method of channel profile analysis, Journal of
Geophysical Research: Earth Surface

### **Conference Presentations and Abstracts**

### 2016

- Valters, D.A. (2016) Frontiers in geomorphological computing. 1st annual Research Software Engineers conference, Manchester, UK.
- Valters, D.A., & Brocklehurst, S. H. (2016) Topographic signatures of spatially-limited storm morphologies revealed from numerical landscape evolution modelling. Geophysical Research Abstracts, EGU General Assembly, Abstract 18-14328.
- Clubb, F.J., Mudd, S.M., Milodowski, D.T., and Valters, D.A. (2016) Geomorphometric delineation of floodplains and terraces from slope and channel relief thresholds, AGU Fall Meeting, Poster.

#### • 2015

- Valters, D.A., Brocklehurst, S. and Schultz, D., (2015). Sensitivity of hydro-geomorphic processes to catchment-scale variations in rainfall distribution. In EGU General Assembly Conference Abstracts (Vol. 17).
- Mudd, S.M., Grieve, S.W.D., Milodowski, D.T., Hurst, M.D., Clubb, F.J., Valters, D.A., (2015) LSDTopo-ToolBox: Open source geomorphology. Presented at the BSG Annual General Meeting, Southampton.

#### 2014

 Valters, D.A. (2014). Modelling landscape sensitivity to stormier climates, British Society for Geomorphology Annual Conference, BSG Annual General Meeting, Manchester

- Valters, D.A. and Mudd, S.M. (2014). Extracting tectonic information using the integral method of river profile analysis: applications along the Wasatch fault, Utah, Geophysical Research Abstracts, EGU General Assembly, Abstract EGU2014-16074-1.
- Mudd, S.M., Attal, M., Milodowski, D.T., Grieve, S.W.D. and Valters, D.A. (2014). A statistical technique for identifying channels of different steepness in transient landscapes, Geophysical Research Abstracts, EGU General Assembly, Abstract EGU2014-15780.

#### **Technical Skills**

### **Programming Languages & Software**

- My current working languages are **C++** and **Python** (including NumPy, Matplotlib). I've experience in writing object-oriented and procedural style code.
- Experience in HPC applications including implementing **OpenMP**-style parallelism, as well as **MPI** approaches to parallelisation.
- Experience in using **subversion** and **git** version control systems.
- Previously I've worked on projects using Javascript and PHP for web development.
- Basic knowledge of Fortran, Matlab, C, and shell scripting in Linux.
- ArcGIS 9 & 10, GRASS-GIS and QGIS.
- Experience in using and modifying the **WRF** numerical weather prediction model and familiarity with the Met Office **Unified Model** (UM).

### **Professional Development**

Programming/Technical courses     Fortran Modernisation     Writing scalable parallel applications with MPI     Advanced MPI     Advanced OpenMP     Message-passing programming with MPI     Single-node performance optimisation     Shared Memory programming with OpenMP     Extended introduction to CUDA	2-3 day courses, provided by ARCHER/EPCC February 2017 December 2016 September 2016 August 2016 July 2016 December 2015 December 2015 November 2015
• Numerical Weather Prediction Model training The Weather Research and Forecasting Model (WRF) Met Office Unified Model (UM)	NCAS/NCAR – October 2013 NCAS/University of Reading – December 2014
Scientific training     NERC/JBA Extreme Flood Forecasting and Management     NCAS Atmospheric Science Summer School	5 days – January 2015 2 weeks – September 2013
<ul> <li>Professional memberships         British Society for Geomorphology         UK Research Software Engineers Network     </li> </ul>	

### Other Roles and Service

<ul> <li>Journal of Open Source Software – reviewer</li> </ul>	2016 – Present
British Society for Geomorphology – Web Officer	2015 – 2017
Teaching Assistant – University of Manchester	2013 – 2016
Courses taught:	

- Fortran and Matlab for engineers
- Earth Surface Processes (Geomorphology)
- Engineering Geology
- Earth Resources
- Our Earth (Open Online Course Moderation)
- Global tectonics

## **Grants and Awards**

- 5th Intel Xeon Phi Access ProgrammeMackay Greenland ScholarshipUndergraduate Class Medal

STFC, Hartree Centre – 4 months trial UoE Award for Greenland-based research project – £1000